Register of the Aleksandr Moiseevich Nekrich Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1962-1996 (Box 18)
  - "Restructuring the Soviet Past: The Politics under Gorbachev" (with Norman Naimark and David Powell), 1990., See also GRANTS/National Endowment for the Humanities (Folder 36: 10-11)
  - "Noble Purpose, Grand Design, Flawed Execution, Mixed Results: Soviet Socialized Medicine after Seventy Years," American Journal of Public Health, 1990 February. (Folder 36: 12)
  - "Eto magicheskoe slovo-suverenitet," 1990 May. (Folder 36: 13)
  - "Prinuditel'nye migratsii v SSSR kak sotsial'no-geograficheskaia problema," 1990 May. (Folder 36: 14)
  - "Razminirovanie polia," 1990 June 3. (Folder 36: 15)
  - "S opozdaniem na piat'desiat let," 1990 July 3. (Folder 36: 16)
  - "Piat' minut molchaniia," 1990 July 17. (Folder 36: 17)
  - "Politika-eto istoriia, oprokinutaia v budushchee," Megapolis-Express, 1990 July 26. (Folder 36: 18)
  - "Politics Aimed at the Future," 1990 September. (Folder 36: 19)
  - "The Dynamism of the Past," 1991. (Box-folder 37: 1)
  - "Staropimenovskii - 5," Detskaia literatuta, 1991. (Folder 37: 2-5)
  - "Nepredvidennye posledstviia," 1991 April. (Folder 37: 6)
  - Broadcast, Radio-Bridge "Radio of Russia" - "Voice of America," 1991 April 16. (Folder 37: 7)
  - "Past Tense," The New York Republic, 1991 April 29. (Folder 37: 8)
  - "K istorii germano-sovietskoi voiny," 1991 June. (Folder 37: 9)
  - "Doroga k voine," Ogonek Magazine, 1991 July. (Folder 37: 10)
  - "Dela nasushchnye," Russkaia mysl, 1991 September 13. (Folder 37: 11)
  - Review of Joachim Hoffman, "Kaukasien 1942/1943," 1992. (Folder 37: 12)
  - "Reexamining Soviet History as Viewed Through Minutes of the Politburo," lecture, Russian Research Center, Harvard University, 1992 February 12. (Folder 37: 13)
  - "K proiasneniiu sovetskogo proshlogo," Russkaia mysl, 1992 March 13. (Folder 37: 14)
  - "V Rossii nachalos' sozdaniie grazdanskogo obshchestva," radio broadcast, Efir-Daidzhest, 1992 April 23. (Folder 37: 15)
  - "Declassifying the Soviet Past," 1992 May. (Folder 37: 16)
  - "Shkola v dvizhenii," 1992 September 28. (Box-folder 38: 1)
  - "Ambitsii I zakon," 1992 October 13. (Folder 38: 2)
  - "Sud'ba reformy," 1992 October 26. (Folder 38: 3)
  - "Novaia opasnost," 1992 November 10. (Folder 38: 4)
  - "V storonu Tikhogo okeana," 1992 November 23. (Folder 38: 5)
  - "Podi tuda-ne znaiu kuda...," 1992 December 7. (Folder 38: 6)
  - "V Berlin I obratno," 1992 December 21. (Folder 38: 7)
  - "Pariahs, Partners, Predators: German-Soviet Relations, 1922-1941," 1993
    - Holograph (Folder 38: 8)
    - Typescript (Folder 38: 9-10)
  - "Start 1993 godu," 1993 January 5. (Folder 38: 11)
  - "Feierverk I rakety," 1993 January 18. (Folder 38: 12)
  - "Povorotnyi punkt," 1993 February 2. (Folder 38: 13)
  - "Novaia amerikanskaia administratsiia I Rossiia," 1993 February 16. (Folder 38: 14)
  - "Partnerstvo-delo oboiudnoe," 1993 March 1. (Folder 38: 15)
  - "Opasnyi povorot," 1993 March 16. (Folder 38: 16)
  - "Po puti konstitutsionnogo perevorota," 1993 March 30. (Folder 38: 17)
  - "Ambitsii I zdravyi smysl," 1993 April 12. (Folder 38: 18)
  - "'Da' - El'tsinu, 'Da' - reformam," 1993 April 26. (Folder 38: 19)
  - "Spusk vniz," 1993 May 25. (Folder 38: 20)
  - "Iiul' - mesiats ozhidanii," 1993 July 6. (Folder 38: 21)
  - Istoriia Rossii,1917-1995, 1996 (Box 39)
    - Research material (Folder 39: 1-8)
    - Research material (Box-folder 40: 1-2)
    - Typescript
      - Outline (Folder 40: 3)
      - Chapter 1 (Folder 40: 4)
      - Chapter 2 (Folder 40: 5)
      - Chapter 3 (Folder 40: 6)
      - Chapter 5 (Folder 40: 7)
      - Chapter 6 (Folder 40: 8)
      - Chapter 7 (Folder 40: 9)
      - Chapter 8 (Folder 40: 10)
      - Chapter 9 (Box-folder 41: 1-2)
      - Chapter 10 (Folder 41: 3)
      - Chapter 11 (Folder 41: 4)
      - Chapter 11 (Folder 42: 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 42: 2-3)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 42: 4-6)
- OBOZRENIIE MAGAZINE, 1982-1986 (Box 43)
  - General (Folder 43: 1)
  - Clippings from the magazine (Folder 43: 2)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1982-1983 (Folder 43: 3)
    - Regarding the possibility of reestablishing publication, 1986-1987 (Folder 43: 4)
  - Illustrations for the magazine (Folder 43: 5-7)
  - Issues of the magazine, 1982 October - 1986 September (Folder 43: 8-9)
- GRANTS, 1976-1992. (Box 44)
  Correspondence, proposals, reports, projects, summaries, outlines
  - Ford Foundation, 1977.
    Includes a report by A. Nekrich for the project "Sunset of the Stalin Era"
  - Hokkaido University, Japan, 1982
  - Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, 1979
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1980
  - National Council for Soviet and East European Research
    - General
    - Research on contemporary problems in the Near and Middle East, 1978-1981
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1977-1980., See also SPEECHES AND WRITINGS/"Restructuring the Soviet Past: The Politics under Gorbachev" (with Norman Naimark and David Powell), 1990
  - Program for Soviet Émigré Scholars, 1976-1978
  - Rockefeller Foundation, 1977-1978
  - Russian Research Center, Harvard University, 1976-1989
  - Smith Richardson Foundation, 1991-1992 (Box 45)
  - Miscellaneous
- SUBJECT FILE, 1940-1991. (Box 46)
  Clippings, conference and seminar programs, correspondence, essays, memoranda, reports, statements
  - Australia, 1981 (Folder 46: 1)
  - Australian Political Studies Association. Annual Conference (23rd: 1981) (Folder 46: 2-3)
  - Conference on Contemporary Soviet Propaganda and Disinformation (1985: Airlie, Va.) (Folder 46: 4-5)
  - Conference on Major Non-Slavic Nationalities of the USSR (1989) (Box-folder 47: 1)
  - Crimean Tatars, 1987-1990 (Folder 47: 2)
  - International Conference on Muslim Minorities (1980: London)
  - Mezhdunarodnyi kongress pamiati A. D. Sakharova "Mir, progress, prava cheloveka" (International Andrey Sakharov Memorial Kongress "Peace, Progress and Human Rights") (1st: 1991: Moscow) (Folder 47: 3)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1991-1994 (Folder 47: 4-5)
  - S"esd narodnykh deputatov. Komissiia po politichskoi I pravovoi otsenke sovetsko-germanskogo dogovora o nenapadenii ot 1939 goda (Congress of people's deputies. Commission on Political and Legal Appraisal of Soviet-German Non Aggression Treaty of 1939) Moscow, 1989 (Folder 47: 6)
  - Socialism - Soviet Union. Typescript by Iakubovskaia entitled "Model' Sotsializma 30-kh Godov," n.d. (Box-folder 48: 1)
  - Soiuz sootechestvennikov (Congress of Compatriots), 1991 (Folder 48: 2)
  - Sovetsko-Amerikanskii simpozium ob otnosheniiakh SSSR I SSHA v gody vtoroi mirovoi voiny (Soviet-American Symposium on US-USSR Relations during World War II) (2nd: 1987: Hyde Park, NY) (Folder 48: 3-5)
  - Stalin, Joseph. Letter to A. Korneichuk, 1940 December 28 (Box-folder 49: 1)
  - Tübingen Conference, 1980. (Folder 49: 2)
    Includes correspondence
  - The Violation of Human Rights in the Soviet Union and the CSCE Follow-up conference in Madrid (Conference) (1980: Cadenabbia, Italy) [CSCE refers to Helsinki Conference, 1975] (Folder 49: 3)
  - World Congress for Soviet and East European Studies (2nd: 1980: Garmisch Partenkirchen, Germany) (Folder 49: 4)
  - Zaiavlenie rodstvennikov sovesti SSSR (Declaration of the relatives of the prisoners of conscience in the USSR), 1976 September 5 (Folder 49: 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 49: 6)
- PRINTED MATTER, 1962-1993 (Box-folder 50-60: 1)
  - General
  - Clippings (Box-folder 60: 2-3)
  - Clippings (Box-folder 61: 1-3)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, n.d. (Box 62)
  - 10 prints depicting A. Nekrich, n.d. (Folder 62: 1)
  - 19 prints of various documents, n.d. (Folder 62: 2)
  - 4 unidentified prints, n.d. (Folder 62: 3)
- AUDIO-VISUAL MATERIAL, n.d.
  - 1 film strip
  - 7 microfilm reels
  - 2 phonotape cassettes